So, indeed, I have spent my life
نعم حتما .. لقد قضيت معظم حياتي
looking into the lives of presidents who are no longer alive.
ادرس حياة الرؤساء السابقين للولايات المتحدة الامريكية
Waking up with Abraham Lincoln in the morning,
كنت استيقظ مع ابراهام لنكولن
thinking of Franklin Roosevelt when I went to bed at night.
وافكر بفرانلين روزفلت في المساء عندما اخلد الى النوم
But when I try and think about what I've learned
ولكن عندما احاول ان افكر عن الذي تعلمته
about the meaning in life, my mind keeps wandering back
عن معنى الحياة .. فعقلي يرجعني
to a seminar that I took when I was a graduate student at Harvard
الى ندوة كنت حضرتها عندما كنت طالبة دراسات عليا في جامعة هارفرد
with the great psychologist Erik Erikson.
مع عالم النفس العظيم إريك إريكسون
He taught us that the richest and fullest lives
لقد علمني ان الاشخاص الاكثر سعادة وعمقاً في عيش الحياة
attempt to achieve an inner balance between three realms:
هم اولئك الذين يستطيعون ان يحققوا التوازن الداخلي بين ثلاثة معطيات
work, love and play.
العمل .. الحب .. واللعب
And that to pursue one realm to the disregard of the other,
وان ملاحقة اي معطى من تلك الثلاث على حساب الاخر
is to open oneself to ultimate sadness in older age.
سوف يدفع الانسان الى التعاسة المطلقة في بقية عمره
Whereas to pursue all three with equal dedication,
بينما ملاحقة المعطيات الثلاث بصورة متوازنة ( متساوية )
is to make possible a life filled not only with achievement,
سوف يجعل الاكتفاء والشعور بالحياة امراً ممكناً ..
but with serenity.
بل وسيعود بالصفاء والسكون على ذلك الشخص جراء ذلك
So since I tell stories, let me look back
وبما انني اقص القصص التاريخية .. دعوني اعود بكم الى الماضي
on the lives of two of the presidents I've studied to illustrate this point --
الى حياة اثنين من رؤسائنا الذين درست مسبقاً لكي اوضح هذه الفكرة
Abraham Lincoln and Lyndon Johnson.
وهما ابراهم لنكولن .. وليندون جونسون
As for that first sphere of work,
ولكي اعطي منحى عام عما ساخبركم
I think what Abraham Lincoln's life suggests
فان حياة ابراهم لنكولن تتأطر ضمن مفهوم
is that fierce ambition is a good thing.
ان الطموح الكبير جداً هو امرٌ جيد
He had a huge ambition.
فقد كان يملك طموحاً غير محدود
But it wasn't simply for office or power or celebrity or fame --
ولم يكن هذا الطموح هدفه منصبٌ .. او سلطة .. او شهرة .. او ثروة
what it was for was to accomplish something worthy enough in life
فقد كان طموحه أن ينجز شيئاً مفيداً حقاً في هذه الحياة
so that he could make the world a little better place for his having lived in it.
كي يستطيع أن يجعل العالم الذي يعيش فيه أفضل و لو بصورة بسيطة
Even as a child, it seemed, Lincoln dreamed heroic dreams.
وحتى في صغره .. فقد كان لنكولن يملك أحلاماً بطولية كبيرة
He somehow had to escape that hard-scrabble farm
فقد حاول ان يتهرب من عمله الصعب في المزرعة
from which he was born.
التي ولد فيها
No schooling was possible for him,
ولم تكن هنالك اي مدرسة تقبل به
except a few weeks here, a few weeks there.
فقد قضى في عدة مدارس فترات لا تتجاوز الاسابيع
But he read books in every spare moment he could find.
ولكنه كان يقرأ الكتب في كل اوقات فراغه
It was said when he got a copy of the King James Bible
وقيل انه عندما حصل على نسخة من انجيل الملك جيمس
or "Aesop's Fables," he was so excited he couldn't sleep.
ونسخة من " خرافات إيسوب " انه لم يستطع النوم حتى أتم تلك الكتب
He couldn't eat.
ولم يأكل ايضاً
The great poet Emily Dickinson once said,
لقد قال الشاعر الكبير إيميلي ديكنسون ذات مرة
"There is no frigate like a book to take us lands away."
"لا يوجد شيءٌ قادرٌ مثل الكتب على أخذنا الى عوالم أخرى "
How true for Lincoln.
وكم كان ذلك صحيحاً في حال لنكولن
Though he never would travel to Europe,
لانه كان يعتقد انه لن يستطيع الذهاب الى اوروبا
he went with Shakespeare's kings to merry England,
فذهب الى انجلترا مع ملوك شكسبير
he went with Lord Byron's poetry to Spain and Portugal.
وذهب الى البرتغال واسبانيا مع شعر لورد بيرون
Literature allowed him to transcend his surroundings.
فقد مكنه الادب من تغيير محيطه وتجاوزه
But there were so many losses in his early life
وتعرض لعدة خسارات في بداية حياته الاولى
that he was haunted by death.
فقد لاحقه الموت كثيراً
His mother died when he was only nine years old;
فتوفيت والدته وهو ابن تسع سنوات
his only sister, Sarah, in childbirth a few years later;
ومن ثم توفيت اخته الوحيدة بعد بضع سنوات
and his first love, Ann Rutledge, at the age of 22.
وحبه الاول " آن روتليدج " توفيت في عامه ال22
Moreover, when his mother lay dying,
و علاوة على ذلك فإن أمه عندما كانت على فراش الموت
she did not hold out for him the hope
لم تمسك يده وتعطيه الامل .. وتخفف عنه
that they would meet in an afterworld.
وتقول له لا تخف سوف نلتقي في الجنة ذات يوم
She simply said to him,
بل قالت له بكل بساطة
"Abraham, I'm going away from you now, and I shall never return."
"إبراهم .. سوف أذهب بعيداً .. ولن أعود أبداً ! "
As a result he became obsessed with the thought
وقد بات مهووساً بهذه الفكرة نتاجاً لتلك الجملة
that when we die our life is swept away -- dust to dust.
اي اننا من التراب الى التراب .. لاشيء بعد الموت
But only as he grew older did he develop
ولكن وعندما كبر في العمر طور
a certain consolation from an ancient Greek notion --
خلاصة جديدة .. استسقاها من الشخصيات الاغريقية القديمة
but followed by other cultures as well --
ومن ثم من الثقافات الاخرى
that if you could accomplish something worthy in your life,
تنص على انه .. ان استطاع الانسان ان يقوم بشيء مفيد حقاً في هذه الحياة
you could live on in the memory of others.
فانه سوف يُخلد في ذاكرة الاخرين
Your honor and your reputation would outlive your earthly existence.
فان اخلاقك .. وسمعتك .. سوف تمد في عمرك مدة أطول من عمر جسدك
And that worthy ambition became his lodestar.
وهذا الطموح " لعمل شيء يغير العالم بصورة مفيدة " اصبح مرشده
It carried him through the one significant depression that he suffered
لقد اخرجه هذا الطموح من الاحباط التام الذي كان يعاني منه
when he was in his early 30s.
عندما كان في الثلاثينيات من عمره
Three things had combined to lay him low.
فقد احبطه حينها ثلاثة امور
He had broken his engagement with Mary Todd,
فسخ خطوبته مع ماري تود
not certain he was ready to marry her,
لانه لم يكن متأكداً من انه مستعد للزواج بها
but knowing how devastating it was to her that he did that.
ولكنه كان متأكداً كم كان ذلك سيؤثر عليها سلباً - فسخ خطوبته -
His one intimate friend, Joshua Speed, was leaving Illinois
وصديقه المقرب جداً . " جوشوا سبيد " كان سيغادر ولاية إلينوي
to go back to Kentucky because Speed's father had died.
لكي يعود الى كنتاكي لان والد "سبيد" توفي حينها
And his political career in the state legislature
وكان عمله السياسي كمشرّع في الولاية
was on a downward slide.
في حالة يرثى لها
He was so depressed that friends worried he was suicidal.
وقد كان محبطاً جداً .. لدرجة ان اصدقاءه خافوا من أن ينتحر
They took all knives and razors and scissors from his room.
فأخذوا كل الشفرات والسكاكين والمقصات التي كانت موجودة في غرفته
And his great friend Speed went to his side and said,
ومن ثم قال له صديقه المقرب " سبيد "
"Lincoln, you must rally or you will die."
لينكولن .. عليك ان تتحرك وتتمالك نفسك .. والا سوف تموت
He said that, "I would just as soon die right now,
فأجابه " اتعلم إن مت الآن
but I've not yet done anything to make any human being
دون ان اقوم بشيء مفيد لاي انسان في هذه الحياة
remember that I have lived."
فلن يتذكرني أحد "
So fueled by that ambition, he returned to the state legislature.
وبهذا الطموح .. عاد الى مجلس الولاية
He eventually won a seat in Congress.
ومن ثم ربح مقعداً في الكونغرس
He then ran twice for the Senate, lost twice.
ومن ترشح مرتين لمنصب السناتور ..وخسر كلاهما
"Everyone is broken by life," Ernest Hemingway once said,
يقول إرنست همنغواي " جميعنا تقسو عليه الحياة...
"but some people are stronger in the broken places."
و لكن بعضنا أكثر قوة في تلك الظروف القاسية "
So then he surprised the nation with an upset victory
ومن ثم فاجأ الامة بنصره بالرئاسة
for the presidency over three far more experienced,
امام ثلاثة مرشحين اكثر خبرة منه
far more educated, far more celebrated rivals.
واكثر علماً .. واكثر شعبية
And then when he won the general election,
ففاز بالانتخابات العامة
he stunned the nation even more
ومن ثم فاجأ الامة اكثر
by appointing each of these three rivals into his Cabinet.
عندما قام بتعيين منافسيه الثلاثة على الرئاسة في فريقه الرئاسي
It was an unprecedented act at the time because everybody thought,
وقد كان تصرفاً خاطئاً حينها كما اعتقد الجميع حينها
"He'll look like a figurehead compared to these people."
فقد قال الناس " انه سيبدو قزماً مقارنة مع هؤلاء الثلاث .. "
They said, "Why are you doing this, Lincoln?"
وسأله البعض " لماذا قمت بهذا لنكولن "
He said, "Look, these are the strongest
فقال .. " ان هؤلاء الثلاثة
and most able men in the country.
هم اقوى واقدر 3 رجال في الدولة
The country is in peril. I need them by my side."
والدولة في حال حرجة .وانا احتاجهم في صفي
But perhaps my old friend Lyndon Johnson
ربما صديقي ليندون جونسن ..
might have put it in less noble fashion:
قد صاغ تلك الاجابة بصورة اقل " رقياً "
"Better to have your enemies inside the tent pissing out,
بقوله " من الافضل ان يكون أعدائك في داخل خيمتك لكي يرمون أوساخهم خارجها
than outside the tent pissing in."
بدل من ان يكونوا في خارجها ويرمون تلك الاوساخ الى داخلها "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it soon became clear that Abraham Lincoln
ولكن خلال فترة وجيزة بات واضحاً أن ابراهام لنكولن
would emerge as the undisputed captain of this unruly team.
قد غدا القائد بلا منازع لذلك الفريق
For each of them soon came to understand
و قد أدرك كل عضو منهم أن لنكولن يملك
that he possessed an unparalleled array of
عدة مهارات على عدة اصعدة
emotional strengths and political skills
في السياسة والعلم والثقافة والمهارات العاطفية
that proved far more important than the thinness of his external résumé.
وقد اثبت ان ذلك أهم بكثير من السيرة الذاتية المنمقة التي كان يملكها الثلاثة
For one thing, he possessed an uncanny ability
وقد كان لامعاً في تعاطفه واستيعابه
to empathize with and to think about other peoples' point of view.
للافكار المختلفة عن افكاره
He repaired injured feelings that might have escalated
واستطاع التغلب على تلك المشاعر السيئة التي نتجت
into permanent hostility.
في محيطه المعادي
He shared credit with ease,
وشارك الجميع بنجاحاته
assumed responsibility for the failure of his subordinates,
وتحمل مسؤوليه فشل بعض خططه .. واخطاء مرؤوسيه
constantly acknowledged his errors and learned from his mistakes.
واعترف باخطائه وتعلم منها
These are the qualities we should be looking for in our candidates in 2008.
وهذه هي الصفات التي يجب ان نبحث عنها في مرشحي الرئاسة 2008
(Applause)
(ضحك)
He refused to be provoked by petty grievances.
ولم يتأثر بالشكاوي التافهة
He never submitted to jealousy or brooded over perceived slights.
ولم يتملكه الغرور بسبب الاضواء التي نالها في رئاسته
And he expressed his unshakeable convictions
وكان بارعاً في سرد حججه المقنعة
in everyday language, in metaphors, in stories.
في اللغة العامية .. وفي الكنايات .. وفي سرد القصص
And with a beauty of language -- almost as if
كان يستخدم المصطلحات الجميلة كما لو
the Shakespeare and the poetry he had so loved as a child
ان شكسبير وشعره الذي احبه في صغره
had worked their way into his very soul.
قد تجسد به واصبح يتحدث على لسانه
In 1863, when the Emancipation Proclamation was signed,
وفي عام 1863 عندما تم توقيع ميثاق تحرير العبيد
he brought his old friend, Joshua Speed, back to the White House,
اعاد صديقه القديم جوشوا سبيد الى البيت الابيض
and remembered that conversation of decades before, when he was so sad.
وتذكر تلك المحادثة التي جرت بينهما عندما كان تعيساً حينها
And he, pointing to the Proclamation, said,
من ثم أشار إلى ميثاق تحرير العبيد و قال:
"I believe, in this measure, my fondest hopes will be realized."
أعتقد أنه بهذا الميثاق ستغدو أغلى آمالي حقيقة
But as he was about to put his signature on the Proclamation
وعندما قدم لكي يوقع الميثاق
his own hand was numb and shaking
كانت يده شبه مخدرة وترتجف
because he had shaken a thousand hands that morning at a New Year's reception.
لانه كان قد صافح الآلاف من الايدي في حفل راس السنة
So he put the pen down.
فوضع القلم جانباً
He said, "If ever my soul were in an act, it is in this act.
وقال " ان كلي ثقة ان هذا الميثاق يجب ان يوقع
But if I sign with a shaking hand,
ولكن ان وقعته ويدي ترتجف
posterity will say, 'He hesitated.'"
سيقول البعض .. لقد تردد
So he waited until he could take up the pen
لذا انتظر قليلاً حتى هدأ .. ومن ثم امسك القلم
and sign with a bold and clear hand.
ووقع بكل ثقة واصرار .. وبيد متمكنة
But even in his wildest dreams,
ولكن حتى في أكبر احلامه
Lincoln could never have imagined
لم يكن لنكولن يتصور
how far his reputation would reach.
ان تصل سمعته حتى هذا المدى
I was so thrilled to find an interview with the great Russian writer,
لقد فوجئت عندما قرأت مقابلة مع كاتب روسي كبير
Leo Tolstoy, in a New York newspaper in the early 1900s.
اسمه ليو تلستوي في مقابلة لصحيفة نيويورك في بداية ال 1900
And in it, Tolstoy told of a trip that he'd recently made
وفيها قص ليو تلستوي قصة رحلة كان قد قام بها مؤخراً
to a very remote area of the Caucasus,
لمنطقة نائية في القوقاز
where there were only wild barbarians,
حيث يعيش هناك برابرة
who had never left this part of Russia.
الذين لم يغادروا تلك المنطقة من روسيا على الاطلاق
Knowing that Tolstoy was in their midst,
وعندما وصل تلستوري الى ارضهم وبات بينهم سُئل
they asked him to tell stories of the great men of history.
لكي يقص قصصاً عن أعظم الرجال في التاريخ
So he said, "I told them about Napoleon
فقال .. لقد اخبرتهم عن " نابليون "
and Alexander the Great and Frederick the Great
والكسندر المقدوني .. وفريدريك العظيم
and Julius Caesar, and they loved it.
والقيصر يوليوس .. وقد احبوا تلك القصص
But before I finished, the chief of the barbarians stood up and said,
ولكن قبل ان انهي السرد .. وقف قائد البرابرة
'But wait, you haven't told us about the greatest ruler of them all.
وقال " انتظر ... انت لم تخبرنا بعد عن حاكم اهم من من ذكرت ..
We want to hear about that man who spoke with a voice of thunder,
أريد ان أسمع عن الرجل الذي كان يتحدث بصوت الرعد
who laughed like the sunrise,
ويضحك كنقاء الشمس
who came from that place called America, which is so far from here,
وجاء من مكان يدعى أمريكا ..وهو مكانٌ بعيدٌ جداً
that if a young man should travel there,
بحيث ان رغب شاباً بالسفر الى هناك
he would be an old man when he arrived.
فإنه سيصل وهو هرم في العمر
Tell us of that man. Tell us of Abraham Lincoln.'"
أخبرنا عن ذلك الرجل .. اخبرنا عن إبراهام لنكولن "
He was stunned.
لقد صعق ليو تلستوري حينها
He told them everything he could about Lincoln.
واخبرهم كل شيء يمكن اخباره عن لنكولن حينها
And then in the interview he said, "What made Lincoln so great?
ومن ثم تحدث في تلك المقابلة عما جعل ابراهم لنكولن عظيماً هكذا ..
Not as great a general as Napoleon,
ليس كونه جنرال حرب مثل نابليون جعله كذلك
not as great a statesman as Frederick the Great."
ولا كونه رجل دولة مثل فريدريك العظيم
But his greatness consisted, and historians would roundly agree,
بل تشكّلت عظمته، و سيجمع المؤرخون، على ان
in the integrity of his character
عظمته جاءت من إتساق شخصيته
and the moral fiber of his being.
ووازعه الاخلاقي الذي رافقه طيلة حياته
So in the end that powerful ambition
مما ادى في النهاية ان يحمله طموحه الكبير
that had carried Lincoln through his bleak childhood had been realized.
خارج ظلام طفولته التي كانت تحيط به
That ambition that had allowed him to laboriously educate himself by himself,
ان ذلك الطموح قد دفعه لان يعلم ويطور نفسه بنفسه
to go through that string of political failures
وان يتجاوز الازمات السياسية
and the darkest days of the war.
والايام العصيبة في اوقات الحروب
His story would be told.
وقصته يجب ان تقص دوماً
So as for that second sphere, not of work, but of love --
بالنسبة للجزء الاخر من القصة .. وهو جزء غير متعلق بالعمل .. بالحب
encompassing family, friends and colleagues --
يشمل العائلة والاصدقاء والزملاء
it, too, takes work and commitment.
وايضاً يحتوي العمل والالتزام
The Lyndon Johnson that I saw in the last years of his life,
ان السنوات الاخيرة التي شهدتها من حياة ليندون جونسون
when I helped him on his memoirs,
عندما ساعدته في كتابة مذكراته
was a man who had spent so many years in the pursuit of
تتحدث عن تلك السنوات الطويلة التي كان قد قضاها ...
work, power and individual success,
في ملاحقة النجاح الوظيفي و النجاح الشخصي ..
that he had absolutely no psychic or emotional resources left
لدرجة استنزاف كل طاقته العاطفية و النفسية (أو الروحية)
to get him through the days
لكي يستطيع ان يستمر بالمضي قدماً
once the presidency was gone.
عندما انتهت فترة رئاسته
My relationship with him began on a rather curious level.
دخلت علاقتي معه منحى آخر ممتلىء بالفضول
I was selected as a White House Fellow when I was 24 years old.
كنت قد اخترت كموظفة في البيت الابيض عندما كنت ابنة 24 عاماً
We had a big dance at the White House.
وكان هناك حفل راقص كبير في البيت الابيض
President Johnson did dance with me that night.
وقد رقص معي الرئيس ليندون جونسون في تلك الليلة
Not that peculiar --
ليس بصورة محددة
there were only three women out of the 16 White House Fellows.
فلم يكن هناك سوى 3 نساء بين موظفي البيت الابيض ال16
But he did whisper in my ear that he wanted me
ولكنه همس في أُذني انه يريدني
to work directly for him in the White House.
ان اعمل مباشرة له في البيت الابيض
But it was not to be that simple.
ولم يكن الامر بهذا البساطة فحسب
For in the months leading up to my selection,
ففي الاشهر التي تلت اختياري ذاك
like many young people, I'd been active
كنت كمعظم الشباب .. ناشطة سياسية
in the anti-Vietnam War movement,
في الحركة المناهضة للحرب في فيتنام
and had written an article against Lyndon Johnson,
وكتبت مقالة ضد الرئيس ليندون جونسون
which unfortunately came out in The New Republic
والتي نشرت لسوء الحظ
two days after the dance in the White House.
بعد يومين من حفل الرقص ذاك في البيت الابيض
(Laugher)
(ضحك)
And the theme of the article was how to remove Lyndon Johnson from power.
وكان محور المقالة كيفية ازالة ليندون جونسون من الرئاسة
So I was certain he would kick me out of the program.
لذا كنت متأكدة انني سوف اطرد من العمل في البيت الابيض
But instead, surprisingly, he said,
ولكن بدلاً من ذلك . .قال لي - مما جعلني اتفاجأ -
"Oh, bring her down here for a year,
" احضروها لكي تعمل هنا لعام ..
and if I can't win her over, no one can."
وان لم استطع ان اكسب وجهة نظرها الى صفنا .. فلن يستطيع أحد القيام بذلك "
So I did end up working for him in the White House.
لذا قد انتهى الامر بي بالعمل في البيت الابيض
Eventually accompanied him to his ranch to help him on those memoirs,
وانتهى الامر بي في النهاية بمساعدته لكتابة مذكراته
never fully understanding why he'd chosen me to spend so many hours with.
ولم اكن متأكدة لم اختارني انا لكي اقضي معه كل هذه الساعات لكتابة كل تلك المذكرات
I like to believe it was because I was a good listener.
كنت اقول لنفسي ربما لانني مستمعة جيدة ..
He was a great storyteller.
وكان هو قاص قصص مميز
Fabulous, colorful, anecdotal stories.
وقصصه كانت ممتعة .. ومثيرة .. وكثيفة
There was a problem with these stories, however,
وكان هنالك مشكلة في هذه القصص
which I later discovered, which is that half of them weren't true.
اكتشفتها لاحقاً .. ان نصف تلك القصص لم تكن صحيحة
But they were great, nonetheless.
ولكنها كانت رائعة جداً ..دون اي شك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I think that part of his attraction for me was that I loved listening to his tall tales.
اعتقد ان جزءاً من اعجابي به .. هو جاذبية تلك القصص .. وكوني احب الاستماع لقصصه الطويلة
But I also worried that part of it was that I was then a young woman.
ولكني كنت متخوفة من كوني صغيرة في العمر
And he had somewhat of a minor league womanizing reputation.
وكان لديه بعض السمعة الغريبة عن كونه محب للنساء
So I constantly chatted to him about boyfriends,
لذا كنت دوما احدثه عن اصدقائي الشباب ..
even when I didn't have any at all.
والذين لم اكن املك اياً منهم
Everything was working perfectly,
كان كل شيء يسير بصورة جيدة
until one day he said he wanted to discuss our relationship.
إلى أن قال في يوم من الأيام إنه يريد ان يناقش علاقتنا
Sounded very ominous when he took me nearby to the lake,
وكان الامر غريباً جداً اذ اخذني الى مكان بقرب بحيرة
conveniently called Lake Lyndon Baines Johnson.
الى بحيرة تدعى " ليندون باينس جونسون "
And there was wine and cheese and a red-checked tablecloth --
وقد كان هناك خمرٌ وجبن .. و مفارش طاولات حمراء
all the romantic trappings.
وكل تلك الامور الرومانسية
And he started out,
ومن ثم بدأ حديثه بقوله
"Doris, more than any other woman I have ever known ... "
دوريس .. انت اكثر إمرأة أعرفها
And my heart sank.
وهنا بدأ قلبي بالخفقان بشدة
And then he said,
ومن ثم قال
"You remind me of my mother."
انت تذكرينني بوالدتي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was pretty embarrassing, given what was going on in my mind.
لقد كنت محرجة جداً بسبب تلك الافكار التي كانت تجول في بالي
But I must say, the older I've gotten,
ولكن يجب ان اقول .. كلما كبرت بالعمر
the more I realize what an incredible privilege it was
لما كبرت بالعمر أدركت مدى الميزة الكبيرة التي كنت أملكها
to have spent so many hours with this aging lion of a man.
تلك التي خولتني ان اجلس مع أسد كبير العمر كل تلك الساعات
A victor in a thousand contests,
ذلك الاسد الذي حقق الالاف من الانتصارات
three great civil rights laws, Medicare, aid to education.
3 منها في مجال الحقوق المدنية والصحة والتعليم
And yet, roundly defeated in the end by the war in Vietnam.
ورغم كل هذا هُزم في النهاية بسبب الحرب في فيتنام
And because he was so sad and so vulnerable,
ولانه كان حزيناً جداً وضعيفٌ جداً
he opened up to me in ways he never would have
فتح قلبه لي بصورة لم يقم بها من قبل
had I known him at the height of his power --
لقد تعرفت على عدة جوانب من شخصيته .. فقد عرفته في قمة قوته
sharing his fears, his sorrows and his worries.
وعرفته وهو يشارك مخاوفه .. واحزانه .. وما يقلقه
And I'd like to believe that the privilege fired within me
و أعتقد أن امتياز وجودي هناك قد اطلق في نفسي
the drive to understand the inner person behind the public figure,
دافعاً لكي افهم النفس الداخلية للشخصيات العامة
that I've tried to bring to each of my books since then.
والتي حاولت ان اسرد خصائصها في الكتب التي اكتبها
But it also brought home to me the lessons
ولكن هذا الامتياز قد اكسبني دروساً كنت اعود بها الى المنزل
which Erik Erikson had tried to instill in all of us
تلك الدروس التي حاول " ايريك اريكسون " ان يزرعها في قلوبنا
about the importance of finding balance in life.
عن اهمية الوصول الى توازن في الحياة
For on the surface, Lyndon Johnson should have had
من الخارج كان ليندون جونسون يجب ان يملك
everything in the world to feel good about in those last years,
كل شيء في العالم يمكنه ان يشعر بصورة جيدة في سنواته الاخيرة
in the sense that he had been elected to the presidency;
فقد تم اختياره كرئيس للولايات المتحدة الامريكية
he had all the money he needed to pursue
وكان يملك كل المال الذي يحتاجه اي شخص لتحقيق احلامه
any leisure activity he wanted;
او لشراء اي وسيلة ترف او رفاهية يريد
he owned a spacious ranch in the countryside, a penthouse in the city,
وكان يملك مزرعة واسعة في الريف ومنزلاً في المدينة
sailboats, speedboats.
وقوارب ابحار .. وقوارب سريعة
He had servants to answer any whim,
وكان لديه طاقم من الخدم ليخدموه على مدار الساعة
and he had a family who loved him deeply.
وكان لديه عائلةٌ تحبه بشدة
And yet, years of concentration solely on work and individual success
وبالاضافة الى تركيزه الدائم على العمل وعلى النجاح الشخصي
meant that in his retirement he could find no solace
عنى انه في فترة تقاعده لم يجد العزاء
in family, in recreation, in sports or in hobbies.
لا في عائلته ولا في هواياته الرياضية ولا في استجمامه
It was almost as if the hole in his heart was so large
كان الامر كما لو انه كان يملك فراغاً كبيراً في قلبه
that even the love of a family, without work, could not fill it.
لم يستطع حب عائلته له .. بدون العمل ان يملأه له
As his spirits sagged, his body deteriorated
فتراجعت معنوياته .. وتدهورت صحته
until, I believe, he slowly brought about his own death.
حتى كما اعتقد جلب لنفسه الموت بيده
In those last years, he said he was so sad
في تلك السنوات الاخيرة كان يقول انه تعيسٌ جداً
watching the American people look toward a new president and forgetting him.
وكان يشاهد الشعب الامريكي وهو ينتخب رئيساً آخر .. وينساه
He spoke with immense sadness in his voice,
وقد كنت أسمع الحزن المرير في صوته
saying maybe he should have spent more time with his children,
وكان يقول انه يجب ان يقضي وقتاً اطول مع اطفاله
and their children in turn.
ومع احفاده
But it was too late.
ولكنه كان قد تأخر بذلك
Despite all that power, all that wealth,
فرغم كل تلك الثروة .. وكل تلك القوة
he was alone when he finally died --
كان وحيداً عندما توفي
his ultimate terror realized.
لقد غدت مخاوفه الكبيرة حقيقةً
So as for that third sphere of play,
بسبب اهماله الجزء الثالث من المعادلة .. اللعب
which he never had learned to enjoy,
فقد كان من اولئك الاشخاص الذين لا يستطيعون الاستمتاع بوقتهم
I've learned over the years
ولقد تعلمت على مدى السنوات
that even this sphere requires a commitment of time and energy --
ان حتى اللعب يحتاج الالتزام والوقت والطاقة
enough so that a hobby, a sport, a love of music,
بصورة كافية .. للهوايات والرياضات .. وحتى حب الموسيقى
or art, or literature, or any form of recreation,
او الادب .. او الفن . .او اي نوع من الاستجمام
can provide true pleasure, relaxation and replenishment.
الذي يمكنه ان يعطي السعادة .. والراحة والتجديد
So deep, for instance, was Abraham Lincoln's love of Shakespeare,
فإبراهم لنكولن كان يحب وليم شكسبير
that he made time to spend more than a hundred nights in the theater,
والذي جعله يقضي مئات الليالي في المسارح
even during those dark days of the war.
حتى في تلك الايام الحالكة في فترات الحرب
He said, when the lights went down and a Shakespeare play came on,
وقال عندما كانت الاضواء تُطفىء .. وتبدأ مسرحية وليم شكسبير
for a few precious hours he could imagine himself
كان يشعر في الساعات الثمينة تلك كان يمكنه ان يتخيل
back in Prince Hal's time.
نفسه في عصر الامير هال
But an even more important form of relaxation for him,
وهذه هواية كانت تدفعه الى الراحة والاستجمام
that Lyndon Johnson never could enjoy,
والتي لم يكن يملكها ليندون جونسون
was a love of -- somehow -- humor,
فلم يكن يشعر بالحب . . او الفكاهة ان صح التعبير
and feeling out what hilarious parts of life can produce
ان الشعور بالفرح والفكاهة في حياتنا يمكنه ان يولد
as a sidelight to the sadness.
جانباً مضيئاً في جوانب الحياة المحزنة
He once said that he laughed so he did not cry,
لقد قال لنكولن يوما ما . .انه كان يضحك .. ولذلك كان لا يبكي
that a good story, for him, was better than a drop of whiskey.
فقد كانت القصة الجميلة التي تقص عليه أهم بكثير من كأس الويسكي
His storytelling powers had first been recognized
لقد كانت قدرته على قص القصص حاضرةً جداً منذ نضوج شخصيته
when he was on the circuit in Illinois.
عندما كان في دائرة في إلينوي
The lawyers and the judges would travel
كان المحامون والقضاة يسافرون
from one county courthouse to the other,
من مقاطعة الى اخرى لكي يروه
and when anyone was knowing Lincoln was in town,
وعندما يتنشر خبر وجود لنولكن في اي مدينة
they would come from miles around to listen to him tell stories.
كان الناس يسافرون من اميال للقدوم والاستماع لقصصه
He would stand with his back against a fire
وكان يقف وظهره الى نار مشتعلة
and entertain the crowd for hours with his winding tales.
ويبدأ بتسلية الجمع بقصصه الممتعة لساعات
And all these stories became part of his memory bank,
وكانت كل تلك الصور تأتي من مخزون ذاكرته
so he could call on them whenever he needed to.
وكان يستطيع ان يستدرك اي قصة يحتاجها في لمح البصر
And they're not quite what you might expect from our marble monument.
والقصص التي كان يقصها ليست تلك التي نتوقعها منه .. صاحب النصب الرخامي
One of his favorite stories, for example,
فواحدة من قصصه التي كان يحبها على سبيل المثال
had to do with the Revolutionary War hero, Ethan Allen.
كانت متعلقة ببطل ثورة الحرب " إيثان آلن "
And as Lincoln told the story,
ويقول لنكولن في تلك القصة
Mr. Allen went to Britain after the war.
ان السيد آلن ذهب الى بريطانيا بعد الحرب
And the British people were still upset
وكان البريطانيون مازالوا يشعرون بالغيظ جراءها
about losing the Revolution,
بسبب هزيمتهم امام الثورة
so they decided to embarrass him a little bit
لذا قرروا ان يحرجوه قليلاً
by putting a huge picture of General Washington
بوضع صورة كبيرة للجنرال واشنطن
in the only outhouse, where he'd have to encounter it.
في دورات المياه الوحيدة .. والتي كان لابد وان يستخدمها
They figured he'd be upset about the indignity
وقد ظنوا ان هذا التصرف سوف يجعله يشعر بالغضب بسبب مهانته ..
of George Washington being in an outhouse.
لوجود صورة لجورج واشنطن في دورة المياه
But he came out of the outhouse not upset at all.
وعندما خرج من دورة المياه لم يكن منزعجاً على الاطلاق
And so they said, "Well, did you see George Washington in there?"
بل قال .. حسناً .. هل رأيتم صورة جورج واشنطن في الداخل ..
"Oh, yes," he said, "perfectly appropriate place for him."
انه المكان الملائم له .. نعم انه كذلك
"What do you mean?" they said.
فسألوه ماذا تعني بذلك ؟
"Well," he said, "there's nothing to make an Englishman shit
فقال . . لا يوجد شيء يجعل البريطانيين .. يبولون بسرعة
faster than the sight of General George Washington."
مثل صورة جورج واشنطن .. من شدة خوفهم !
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So you can imagine, if you are in the middle of a tense cabinet meeting --
تخيلوا ان تكونوا في موقف يشوبه التوتر .. وهناك
and he had hundreds of these stories --
شخص مثل هذا الرئيس ولديه المئات من هذه القصص
you would have to relax.
سوف تشعر بالاسترخاء حتماً
So between his nightly treks to the theater,
إذا .. بين تلك الليالي التي قضاها في المسارح
his story telling, and his extraordinary sense of humor
وبين قدرته على قص القصص .. وحسه الكبير للفكاهة
and his love of quoting Shakespeare and poetry,
وحبه للاقتباس من شعر واقوال شكسبير
he found that form of play which carried him through his days.
وجد نمطاً من اللعب والفكاهة لكي يرافقه في مسيرة حياته
In my own life, I shall always be grateful
في حياتي انا . يجب ان اكون ممتنة
for having found a form of play in my irrational love of baseball.
لاني وجدت اللعب في حياتي بسبب حبي غير منطقي للعبة البيسبول
Which allows me, from the beginning of spring training
والذي يجعلني من بداية تدريبات الربيع
to the end of the fall,
وحتى نهاية الخريف
to have something to occupy my mind and heart
مشغولة الفكر والقلب
other than my work.
بشيء غير عملي
It all began when I was only six years old,
ولقد بدأ الامر عندما كنت ابنة 6 اعوام
and my father taught me that mysterious art of keeping score
عندما علمني والدي الفن السري للمحافظة على نتيجة مبارة البيسبول
while listening to baseball games --
عندما كنت استمع لها على جهاز الراديو
so that when he went to work in New York during the day,
عندما كان يذهب للعمل في نيويورك اثناء النهار
I could record for him the history of that afternoon's
كنت احفظ له كل ما يحدث في مبارايات
Brooklyn Dodgers game.
بروكلين دوجرز
Now, when you're only six years old,
عندما تكون ابن ست سنوات
and your father comes home every single night
ووالدك يعود كل ليلة
and listens to you -- as I now realize that I, in excruciating detail,
ويستمع اليك .. وكما ادركت اليوم .. كنت اقص التفاصيل الدقيقة جداً
recounted every single play of every inning
كل تفصيل من اللعبة .. كل من دخل وكل من خرج
of the game that had just taken place that afternoon.
وكل شيء حدث في تلك اللعبة
But he made me feel I was telling him a fabulous story.
وجعلني اشعر انني اقص قصة عظيمة
It makes you think there's something magic about history
وجعلني اشعر بشيء مثير نحو التاريخ واعادة سرد الاحداث
to keep your father's attention.
خاصة عندما استطيع جذب انتباه والدي
In fact, I'm convinced I learned the narrative art
في الحقيقة انا مقتنعة انني تعلمت فن السرد
from those nightly sessions with my father.
من تلك الليالي التي قضيتها مع والدي وانا اسرد له الاحداث
Because at first, I'd be so excited I would blurt out,
ففي بداية الامر .. كنت احرق القصة فأصرخ قائلةً ما إن اراه
"The Dodgers won!" or, "The Dodgers lost!"
لقد ربح فريق دوجرز ... لقد خسر فريق دوجرز ..
Which took much of the drama of this two-hour telling away.
مما كان يحرق القصة التي كانت تستغرق ساعتين عادة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I finally learned you had to tell a story
ولكن في النهاية تعلمت كيفية القاء القصص
from beginning to middle to end.
من البداية الى الحبكة الى النهاية
I must say, so fervent was my love
وانا يجب اقول .. ان حبي للبيسبول كان متقداً جداً
of the old Brooklyn Dodgers in those days
وحبي للبروكلين دوجرز في تلك الايام
that I had to confess in my first confession
اضطررت ان اعترف في اعترافي الاول للقس في الكنسية
two sins that related to baseball.
بذنبين كانا متعلق بالبيسبول
The first occurred because the Dodgers' catcher, Roy Campanella,
الاول كان متعلق بمتلقي الكرات لفريق دوجرز .. روي كامبنيلا
came to my hometown of Rockville Centre, Long Island,
حيث جاء الى مدينتنا في لونج آيسلند
just as I was in preparation for my first Holy Communion.
وانا كنت استعد حينها لقرباني المقدس الاول
And I was so excited --
وكنت متحمسة جداً
first person I'd ever see outside of Ebbets Field.
فقد كان الشخص الاول الذي اراه من خارج " حقول ايبتس "
But it so happened he was speaking in a Protestant Church.
وكان سيتحدث في كنسية بروستانتية
When you are brought up as a Catholic, you think
واذا كنت كاثوليكيا . .فانت تفكر
that if you ever set foot in a Protestant Church,
انه ما ان تلمس رجلك الكنيسة البروستانتية
you'll be struck dead at the threshold.
حتى تصيبك صاعقة ترديك قتيلاً
So I went to my father in tears, "What are we going to do?"
فذهب الى القس باكية .. وقلت له " مالذي يجب ان اقوم به حيال هذا ؟ "
He said, "Don't worry. He's speaking in a parish hall.
فقال لي لا تقلقي .. سوف يتحدث في قاعة الرعية
We're sitting in folding chairs. He's talking about sportsmanship.
وكنا نجلس في مكان بعيد قليلاً .. وكان يتحدث عن الرياضة
It's not a sin."
فهذه ليست الخطيئة
But as I left that night, I was certain that somehow
ولكن بعد تلك الليلة كنت متأكدة بصورة ما
I'd traded the life of my everlasting soul
انني ابادل حياتي
for this one night with Roy Campanella.
بتلك الليلة التي قضيتها مع روي كامبانيلا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And there were no indulgences around that I could buy.
وليس هنالك تعلق بهذا النحو يمكن ان يحصل عليه شخص ما في هذه الحياة
So I had this sin on my soul when I went to my first confession.
إذاً هذه هي خطيئة الاولى .. التي تحدثت عنها في اعترافي الاول
I told the priest right away.
الذي قمت به للقس حينها مباشرة
He said, "No problem. It wasn't a religious service."
فقال لي " لا عليك .. لم تكن خدمة دينية ..
But then, unfortunately, he said, "And what else, my child?"
ولكن للاسف قال لاحقاً .. وماذا ايضاً يا بنيتي ؟ "
And then came my second sin.
ومن ثم قصصت خطيئتي الثانية
I tried to sandwich it in between talking too much in church,
لقد كنت ادخل بين ادعيتي التي كنت تعلمتها في الكنيسة
wishing harm to others, being mean to my sisters.
الرغبة بإيذاء الاخرين .. وان اكون قاسية مع اخواني
And he said, "To whom did you wish harm?"
فسئلتي القس " لمن كنت تتمنين الأذى ؟ "
And I had to say that I wished that various New York Yankees players
فقلت له انني كنت اتمناه للاعبي فريق نيويورك يانكيز
would break arms, legs and ankles --
كنت اتمنى .. ان تكسر ايديهم .. وارجلهم .. وركبهم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- so that the Brooklyn Dodgers could win their first World Series.
لكي يربح فريق بروكلين دوجرز في الدوري العالمي الاول
He said, "How often do you make these horrible wishes?"
فقال : كم مرة قمتِ بالدعاء بأدعية سيئة ؟
And I had to say, every night when I said my prayers.
فقلت له كل يوم .. في دعواتي الليلية كنت اقول ذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So he said, "Look, I'll tell you something.
فقال لي .. حسناً دعيني اخبرك شيئاً
I love the Brooklyn Dodgers, as you do,
انا احب فريق بروكلين دوجرز ايضا .. كما تحبينه انت
but I promise you some day they will win fairly and squarely.
وانا اعدك انه يوما ما سوف يربحون بكل عدل وسوف يستحقون ربحهم بكل جدارة
You do not need to wish harm on others to make it happen."
ولا حاجة في ان تتمني الاذى للاخرين لكي يقوموا بذلك
"Oh yes," I said.
فقلت " حسناً "
But luckily, my first confession -- to a baseball-loving priest!
من حسن حظي ان اعترافي الاول كان لقس يحب البيسبول
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well, though my father died of a sudden heart attack
ومن ثم توفي والدي بسبب أزمة قلبية مفاجئة
when I was still in my 20s,
عندما كنت ابنة 20 عاماً
before I had gotten married and had my three sons,
قبل ان اتزوج وانجب اطفالي الثلاث
I have passed his memory -- as well as his love of baseball -- on to my boys.
لقد قمت بنقل ولعه الشديد في البيسبول وكل ذكرياته الى اولادي
Though when the Dodgers abandoned us to come to L.A.,
بحيث عندما ترك الدوجرز مدينتنا للذهاب الى مدينة لوس انجلس
I lost faith in baseball until I moved to Boston
فقدت الايمان بالبيسبول .. حتى انتقلت الى بوسطن
and became an irrational Red Sox fan.
وغدا ولعي الشديد موجهاً نحو فريق " الريد سوكس "
And I must say, even now, when I sit with my sons
ويجب ان اقول . .انه وحتى اليوم ..وانا اجلس مع ابنائي
with our season tickets,
ونحن نملك التذاكر الموسمية للفريق
I can sometimes close my eyes against the sun
استطيع من حين الى اخر ان اغلق عيني أمام الشمس
and imagine myself, a young girl once more, in the presence of my father,
واتخيل نفسي .. طفلة صغيرة مرة اخرى في حضور والدي
watching the players of my youth on the grassy fields below:
اشاهد اولئك اللاعبين الذين كانوا يلعبون في ذلك الوقت في هذه الملاعب العشبية
Jackie Robinson, Roy Campanella, Pee Wee Reese, and Duke Snider.
مثل " جاكي روبنسون . روي كامبينيلا . بي وي ريسي . و دوك سنايدر "
I must say there is magic in these moments.
ويجب ان اقول ان هناك سحراً في تلك اللحظات
When I open my eyes and I see my sons
وعندما افتح اعيني .. وارى اطفالي
in the place where my father once sat,
في المكان الذي اجلسني فيه والدي ذات يوم
I feel an invisible loyalty and love
اشعر بالولاء والحب تجاهه
linking my sons to the grandfather whose face they never had a chance to see,
لانني قمت بعمل وصل بين والدي وبين ابنائي ..الذين لم تسنح لهم الفرصة للقائه
but whose heart and soul they have come to know
ولكنهم التقوا . .بشغفه وحبه وروحه
through all the stories I have told.
عبر كل تلك القصص التي كنت اسردها لهم عنهم
Which is why, in the end, I shall always be grateful for this curious love of history,
والذي في النهاية .. علي ان اكون ممتنة له بسبب ولعي الشغوف بالتاريخ
allowing me to spend a lifetime looking back into the past.
فقد جعلني ذلك اعود الى الوراء الى الماضي
Allowing me to learn from these large figures
لكي اتعلم من هؤلاء الرموز الكبيرة
about the struggle for meaning for life.
عن معنى الحياة .. وعن كيفية المضي قدماً
Allowing me to believe that the private people
وعلمني حبي ذلك .. كيف ان الاشخاص المقربين لنا
we have loved and lost in our families,
واحبائنا .. الذين فقدنا في عائلاتنا
and the public figures we have respected in our history,
والرموز الوطنية الكبيرة التي نحترم في تاريخنا
just as Abraham Lincoln wanted to believe,
مثل ابراهم لنكولن .. جعلني أؤمن
really can live on, so long as we pledge
انهم يمكنهم ان يستمروا في العيش معنا .. طالما أردنا ذلك
to tell and to retell the stories of their lives.
وطالما استمررنا في سرد القصص واعادة سردها عن حياتهم
Thank you for letting me be that storyteller today.
شكراً لانكم سمحتم لي بأن أكون قاصة قصص اليوم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً